<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/ns/document-metadata" generator="Adobe Captivate 5">
<document-info>
	<title></title>
	<summary></summary>
	<author></author>
	<keywords>Adobe Captivate Project </keywords>
	<view-link href="Nutrition.swf?slide={position}"/>
</document-info>
<section type="slide" position="1">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>BASIC NUTRITION FOR PERSONAL TRAINERS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="2">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>Live the dream!</text>

	<text>BASIC NUTRITION FOR PERSONAL TRAINERS</text>

	<text>COURSE OUTCOMES</text>

	<text>COURSE OVERVIEW</text>

	<text>You will be provided with a certificate after successfully completing the “Nutrition for Personal Trainers” course requirements,The Nutrition course entitles you to 13 CEC points.</text>

	<text>Dietary BasicsMacronutrients, namely Carbohydrate, Fats and ProteinsFood label readingPre and Post Workout MealsPopular Diets Artificial Sweeteners</text>

	<text>NUTRITION FOR PERSONAL TRAINERS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="3">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>

	<text>Dietary analysis is often comprised of two parts, needs and intake. </text>

	<text>Optimal nutrition is often referred to as a matter of energy balance  (energy-in versus energy-out) however there are many variables that need to be considered. </text>

	<text>The body does not simply operate on a mathematical equation as there are many factors that need to be taken into consideration in the total preparation of ones diet. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="4">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>Metabolic rate - The term metabolic rate can be divided into three components: </text>

	<text>Basal metabolic rate (BMR)- is the amount of kilojoules burned at rest and contributes 50-80 per cent of your energy used. </text>

	<text>Energy used during physical activity- this is the amount of kilojoules or calorie burned during movement and physical activity; in a normally active person, this component contributes 20 per cent of daily energy use. </text>

	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>

	<text>Thermic effect of food - this is the energy you use to eat, digest and metabolise food. It contributes about 5-10 per cent of your energy use.</text>

	<text>ENERGY OUTPUT</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="5">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>

	<text>BASAL METABOLIC RATE OR RESTING ENERGY EXPENDITURE</text>

	<text>BMR is the energy required for cellular and tissue processes that maintain physiological functions at rest, Muscular activity contributes slightly on BMR.BMR can also be referred as the energy the body needs to maintain itself in the sedentary stateThough every individual has a slightly different BMR, the average of the energy expenditure rate is about 70 calories per hour. Slightly more when we are awake but slightly less when we are sleeping.Many factors such as gender, muscle mass, body temperature and age can affect BMR.</text>

	<text>Men usually use more calories than women.The more the lean muscle mass, the higher the BMR is. This is also the reason why we need to build up more muscles because you can burn more calories!BMR decreases with age.More energy will be used to generate heat under low temperature.</text>

	<text>BMR however is mainly determined by genetics and general physiological factors. Only proper diets where it includes balanced proportion of fats, carbohydrates and proteins together with age-appropriate exercise will assist in achieving your fitness and weight loss goals.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="6">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ENERGY FOR PHYSICAL ACTIVITY</text>

	<text>It can increase a person’s metabolism due to moderate and strenuous physical activity.The exact amount of energy this accounts for depends on the physiological ‘’cost’’ of the activity.For example, when we move, we need energy for muscle movement. And that creates the ‘’cost’’ of activity.How fast we move is one of the factors on how much energy we spend. The faster you move, the more energy you use given in the same amount of exercise time. For example, running takes more energy than pilates class under the same time output.</text>

	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="7">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>Practical strategy : Small and frequent meal,</text>

	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>

	<text>Due to the thermic effect of food, after ingesting any food, it uses energy for digestion, absorption and metabolize the food.</text>

	<text>Why it works?</text>

	<text>This means, the more the TIMES you eat, the more the energy you will consume.</text>

	<text>Also, skipping meals will just make you eat more in the next meals.</text>

	<text> If you overload your body with food, where your body cannot  use the energy in time, it will be converted to fat for storage.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="8">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>THERMIC EFFECT OF FOOD</text>

	<text>It is the energy used due to the cost of processing food for storage and useIn other words, it is the energy expended by our bodies to process food. It usually referred to digestion, absorption and metabolism of food.Different marconutrients require different energy levels for process and as such can be more predisposed to be stored as fat. Discussion: you may probably hear of high protein diet for weight loss purpose. Why do you think high protein meals help to lose more energy? Try to answer that at the end of this part.The term ‘’thermic effect of food’’ is used to describe the energy expended by our bodies in order to consume (by biting, chewing and swallowing) and process (from digestion, transportation, metabolism and storage) food.  We ‘’expend energy’’ by burning calories.Processing protein requires the most energy among the three macronutrients. It is estimated to be as high as 30% of the calories consumed.Dietary fat on the other hand requires the least energy. It is more easily processed and converted to body fat. The thermic effect can be as little as 2-3%.The energy for processing carbohydrates is in between that of the protein and fat. It is about 5-10%</text>

	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="9">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>

	<text>THERMIC EFFECT OF FOOD</text>

	<text>Your BMR is increased after eating because you use energy for digesting, metabolizing and absorbing the food.This rise occurs once you start eating and reaches the peaks after 2 to 3 hours upon eating. </text>

	<text>As mentioned before, different macronutrients contributes different percentage the energy use due to the thermic effect of food. Here is the reference:Fat: raises BMR around 3%.Carbohydrates: raises BMR about 8%.And protein raises BMR up to 30%. </text>

	<text>(*Answer to the question:  When you consume the same amount of protein, carbohydrate and fat, protein takes the most energy for metabolizing, following by carbohydrate and then fat. It is because it takes more energy to metabolize amino acids into fat then to convert glucose into glycogen or transfer absorbed fat into adipose store. That is to say, protein has the highest thermic effect of food while fat has the lowest.)(*Answer to the question:  When you consume the same amount of protein, carbohydrate and fat, protein takes the most energy for metabolizing, following by carbohydrate and then fat. It is because it takes more energy to metabolize amino acids into fat then to convert glucose into glycogen or transfer absorbed fat into adipose store. That is to say, protein has the highest thermic effect of food while fat has the lowest.) </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="10">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>THERMIC EFFECT OF FOOD</text>

	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>

	<text>As you can see, all calories are not equal. If you eat an equal number of calories of protein, fat and carbohydrates, the calories in the fat are more likely to end up on your waist as fewer of them are burned off by the thermic effect.A figure of 10% is generally used to account for the thermic effect of food.This means that if you want to replace 500 calories burned through activity, you need to eat 10% more, or 550 calories. And if you eat 500 calories, 10% of them will be burned off by the thermic effect, leaving only 450. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="11">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>LIFESTYLE FACTORS</text>

	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>

	<text>When designing a diet or advising regarding a person dietary habits there are a host of factors that must be taken into consideration to promote success. Some things to consider are: </text>

	<text>Food likes and dislikes,Occupation,Cultural differences,Vegetarian, Vegan,Emotional connections to food, Time availability,Knowledge of food choices,Food allergies,Financial constraints,Level of commitment / dedication</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="12">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>THE NEED FOR DIETARY ANALYSIS FOR ATHLETES</text>

	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>

	<text>Lack of fibrous carbohydrates (vegetables), sometimes none at all,Over-consumption of junk food,Severe energy deficits, especially from endurance athletes, young athletes just moved out from home, excessively thin female athletes,Poor Iron, Calcium, Zinc, B vitamins, and nitrogen levels in vegetarian athletesApproximately 80-90% of the general population have inappropriate zinc intake (ACSM 2000) and 10% of female athletes have iron deficiencies.Insufficient consumption of protein intakes by lazy athletes and not enough essential fatty acids in their diet (EFA’s).Many athletes forget to eat breakfast and/or skip lunch.</text>

	<text>Many athletes have remarkably poor nutritional habits such as: </text>

	<text>1.</text>

	<text>2.</text>

	<text>3.</text>

	<text>4.</text>

	<text>5.</text>

	<text>6.</text>

	<text>7.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="13">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>SHOULD PERSONAL TRAINERS BE DOING NUTRITIONAL ANALYSIS?Controversial Question…</text>

	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>

	<text>Remembering the personal trainer is simply writing a suggested diet for healthy individuals.As a fitness trainer, if you encounter medical conditions which require specific dietary intake, Then you must realise that there are limitations in you providing this type of nutritional information,Therefore you should be aware of allied health professionals who can assist or, alternatively, you may be able to recommend one. </text>

	<text>“It is well within the scope of practice of the personal trainer who possesses fundamental nutrition knowledge to address misinformation and give advice as it relates to general nutrition for physical performance, disease prevention, weight loss, and weight gain.” (NSCA Essentials of Personal Training p 122, 2004). </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="14">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>DIETARY BASICS</text>

	<text>This applies particularly if you have identified any, or potential health issues in the trainee, Remembering this equally applies to any other medical conditions as well.</text>

	<text>DieticiansSports PhysiciansMedical practitionersPhysiotherapistsPodiatristsMassage therapistsChiropractors</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="15">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>Carbohydrates belong to a class of substances called macronutrients, meaning nutrients that the body needs in large amountsCarbohydrates are an important macro nutrient for the body as they are the main providers of energy to drive metabolic reactions Carbohydrates are also the preferred fuel source for brain function</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="16">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>The main elements that make up Carbohydrates are Carbon, Hydrogen, and Oxygen (C-H-O)Most carbohydrates have a ratio of 1:2:1 of carbon, hydrogen, and oxygen, respectivelyCarbohydrates can be classified in three main groups</text>

	<text>MonosaccharidesDisaccharidesPolysaccharides</text>

	<text>ELEMENTS OF  CARBOHYDRATES</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="17">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>MONOSACCHARIDES</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>These are single molecules of sugar.The monosaccharide&apos;s are: </text>

	<text>Glucose - is found in most carbohydrate foods including sugars and starches. They are the building blocks of carbohydrate. Glucose is the main energy supplying molecule for the bodyFructose - is also known as fruit sugar and thus is found in fruits. It is converted into glucose by the liver, andGalactose- is part of lactose, the sugar found in milk.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="18">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>DISACCHARIDES</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>These are two linked sugar molecules which are broken down into the monosaccharide&apos;s by digestion.The disaccharides are:	 	</text>

	<text>Sucrose 	= glucose + fructoseLactose 	= glucose + galactoseMaltose     = glucose + glucose</text>

	<text>Sucrose (table sugar) normally comes from sugar cane.Lactose  is found in milk and milk products. 	Maltose  is formed when starch is broken down.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="19">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>STARCHES</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>Starch is simply hundreds of molecules of glucose sugar joined together. When starch is digested, it is first broken down into maltose and then into glucose. There are generally two (2) types of carbohydrates often referred to in dietary recommendations; that is; starchy and fibrous carbohydrates. Starchy carbohydrates broadly fall into things like breads, pasta, rice and cereals. Fibrous Carbohydrates are generally predominantly anything green, e.g.: vegetables salads. 	 	</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="20">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>GLYCEMIC INDEX (GI)What is the glycemic index?</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>Low			    	0 – 55 Moderate			56 – 69High				70 or more</text>

	<text>A scale that ranks carbohydrates by how much they raise blood glucose levels compared to a reference food</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="21">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>GLYCEMIC INDEX (GI) - PROTOCOLS</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>25 or 50 grams carbohydrate of test food.Blood samples taken:1st hour: every 15 minutes2nd hour: every 30 minutes3rd hour: every 30 minutes*</text>

	<text>SAMPLE GRAPHS</text>

	<text>1.</text>

	<text>2.</text>

	<text>3.</text>

	<text>1.</text>

	<text>2.</text>

	<text>Values plotted; AUC calculated.Test food response compared to reference food response.Average GI of 8-10 volunteers = GI of test food</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="22">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ISSUES INFLUENCING GI RANKING </text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>STARCH</text>

	<text>Amylose</text>

	<text>                  Absorbs less waterMolecules form tight clumpsSlower rate of digestion</text>

	<text>Amylopectin</text>

	<text>                  Absorbs more waterMolecules are more openFaster rate of digestion</text>

	<text>Lower GI</text>

	<text>                  Kidney beans (28)Uncle Ben’s converted LG rice (50)</text>

	<text>Higher GI</text>

	<text>                  Russet potato (85)Glutinous rice (98)</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="23">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ISSUES INFLUENCING GI RANKING PHYSICAL ENTRAPMENT</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>Lower GI                    All Bran (38)Umpernickelbread (50)Higher GIBagel (72)Corn Flakes (92)</text>

	<text>Bran acts as a physical barrier that slows down enzymatic activity on the internal starch layer.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="24">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ISSUES INFLUENCING GI RANKING VISCOSITY OF FIBRE</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>Lower GI                    Apple (40)Rolled oats (51)</text>

	<text>Viscous, soluble fibers transform intestinal contents into gel-like matter that slows down enzymatic activity on starch.</text>

	<text>Higher GI                   Whole wheat bread (73)Cheerios (74)</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="25">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ISSUES INFLUENCING GI RANKING SUGAR CONTENT</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>Viscous, soluble fibers transform intestinal contents into gel-like matter that slows down enzymatic activity on starch.</text>

	<text>Sugar    			Sucrose    		           Glucose + Fructose		(GI 60)        	         (GI 100)        		                  (GI 19)</text>

	<text>Starch     		         Maltose    		           Glucose + Glucose	      (GI 105)        		(GI 100)      		                 (GI 100)</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="26">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ISSUES INFLUENCING GI RANKING FAT AND PROTEIN CONTENT</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>Lower GI                    Peanut M&amp;M’s (33)Potato chips (54)Special K (69)Higher GIJelly beans (78)Baked potato (85)Corn Flakes (92)</text>

	<text>Fat and protein slow down gastric emptying, and thus, slows down digestion of starch.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="27">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ISSUES INFLUENCING GI RANKING ACID CONTENT</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>Lower GI                    Sourdough wheat bread (54)</text>

	<text>Acid slows down gastric emptying, and thus, slows down the digestion of starch.</text>

	<text>Higher GIWonder white bread (73)</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="28">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ISSUES INFLUENCING GI RANKING FOOD PROCESSING</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>Lower GI                    Old fashioned, rolled oats (51)Higher GIQuick, 1-minute oats (66)</text>

	<text>Highly processed foods require less digestive processing.</text>

	<text>COOKING</text>

	<text>Lower GI                    Al dente spaghetti – boiled 10 to 15 minutes (44)Higher GIOver-cooked spaghetti – boiled 20 minutes (64)</text>

	<text>Cooking swells starch molecules and softens foods, which speeds up the rate of digestion.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="29">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>FACTORS INFLUENCING GI RANKING</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>Type of starch</text>

	<text>Physical entrapment</text>

	<text>Viscosity of fiber</text>

	<text>Sugar content</text>

	<text>Cooking</text>

	<text>Food processing</text>

	<text>Acid Content</text>

	<text>Protein Content</text>

	<text>Fat content</text>

	<text>How does all this affect our glycemic levels?How does all this make us feel after eating carbohydrate-containing foods?</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="30">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>Examples of LOW (55 or less) GI foods:</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>                  Roasted peanuts 	         	rating of 14All Brand cereal		                 rating of 42Porridge with water     	        rating of 42Carrots				        rating of 47Sweet Corn     			        rating of 54</text>

	<text>Examples of MEDIUM (56 – 69) GI foods:</text>

	<text>                  Basmati rice 			        rating of 58Raisins			     	        rating of 64Rye bread			                rating of 65Weetbix				        rating of 69</text>

	<text>Examples of HIGH (70+) GI foods:</text>

	<text>                  White bread 			       rating of 70Popcorn				       rating of 72Baked Potatoes 		       rating of 85Corn flakes			       rating of 92</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="31">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ISSUES INFLUENCING GI RANKING</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>                   Glycemic load measures the degree of glycemic response and insulin demand produced by a specific amount of a specific food.Glycemic load reflects both the quality and the quantity of dietary carbohydrates.  </text>

	<text>GLYCEMIC LOAD (GL)</text>

	<text>                   The glycemic load  is a relatively new way to assess the impact of carbohydrate consumption  but gives a fuller picture as opposed to the glycemic index alone,GL simply tells you how much carbohydrate there actually is found in a carbohydrate food. A GI value tells you only how rapidly a particular carbohydrate turns into sugar. You need to know both things to understand a food&apos;s effect on blood sugar.  </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="32">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>GLYCEMIC INDEX (GI)</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>                   Watermelon has a high GI, but compared to other foods you might eat, it doesn’t have as much carbohydrate because it is mainly water.The small amount of carbohydrate in watermelon is absorbed very quickly making it a high-GI food, but because there is so little it won’t have much effect on your blood glucose levels, so in terms of impact, it is very low. This is termed ‘glycemic Load’.A good web page to find out Glycemic index and Glycemic loads of many popular Australian foods is… www.glycemicindex.com </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="33">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>GLYCEMIC INDEX (GI)</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>                   The GI in particular has grown tremendously in popularity of late and does offer some benefits in selecting healthy carbohydrate sources. Consequently it also has some limitations associated with it and as such many food manufacturers have exploited this fact to the unsuspecting buyer. </text>

	<text>Some of these limitations are:</text>

	<text>                   Carbohydrates are measured in a fasted state so only really applies to breakfast (Break – Fast), Combining carbohydrates with other macro nutrients (fats, protein) can change the GI rating significantly, Carbohydrates generally (there are exceptions) aren’t eaten by themselves thus won’t have a true score based on the GI rating,GI does not demonstrate the total carbohydrate content </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="34">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>FOOD LABELLING BASED ON GI ENDORSEMENT OR LISTING</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>                   When making suitable food choices many people will look at products that have listed on their labelling a low GI for example. With these food choices the real key is to look at the ingredient list as this is something that has to be listed correctly by legislation and gives you the true picture of what you are eating. The ingredient list is always listed from the most to the least.There are many products that claim to have a low GI but list sugar as their first (most) ingredient in the total product.  </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="35">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>SUGAR HAS THE HIGHEST GI RATING?</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>                   To do this they simply combine fats with the sugar which slows its absorption rate thus changing the GI factor. It is well known and recommended by the GI advocates to avoid or minimise sugar content as much as possible in any foods consumed. </text>

	<text>                   “I was told to eat lots of fruit to lose weight… is this true?”</text>

	<text>                   Fruit does have some great benefits including it tastes great! It is a good source of vitamins and minerals and is easily available to everyone, i.e.; when you are on the road, travelling etc.Ok but how does it relate to the person trying to lose some FAT. First you may have heard of fructose which is fruit sugar.    </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="36">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>SUGAR HAS THE HIGHEST GI RATING?</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - CARBOHYDRATES</text>

	<text>                   Fructose is primary used by the liver in two ways, used as energy (converted to glycogen) or into triglycerides (fat). To convert it to energy, which is the best situation we want, it is achieved through an enzymatic process via the liver. However there can be a problem if we consume too much fruit in one day as the liver has limited fructose-converting enzyme. Most people on average can only convert about 50 grams (200 calories) of fructose to glycogen per day then the rest is converted to FAT. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="37">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>UNSATURATED FATS</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - FATS</text>

	<text>                   Fats are organic compounds that are made up of carbon, hydrogen, and oxygen; they are the most concentrated source of energy in foods. Fats belong to a group of substances called lipids.Fats come in liquid or solid form. They provide nine calories per gram, more than twice the number provided by carbohydrates or protein. Eating too much saturated fat in particular is one of the major risk factors for heart disease.</text>

	<text>                   Fats that help to lower blood cholesterol if used in place of saturated fats Most (but not all) liquid vegetable oils are unsaturated.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="38">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>MONO-UNSATURATED FATS</text>

	<text>                   Fats that help to lower blood cholesterol if used in place of saturated fats. However, mono-unsaturated fats have a lot of calories, so you still need to limit them. Examples include olive and canola oils. </text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - FATS</text>

	<text>POLYUNSATURATED FATS</text>

	<text>                   Fats that help to lower blood cholesterol if used in place of saturated fats. However, polyunsaturated fats have a lot of calories, so you still need to limit them. Examples include safflower, sunflower, corn, and soybean oils.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="39">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>TRANS FATTY ACIDS</text>

	<text>                   These fats form when vegetable oil hardens (a process called hydrogenation).They can lower HDL levels (&quot;good cholesterol&quot;). These are found in fried foods, commercial baked goods, processed foods, and margarines. These should be avoided as much as possible as they are linked to heart disease. </text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - FATS</text>

	<text>HYDROGENATED</text>

	<text>                   Refers to oils that have become hardened (such as hard butter and margarine). Foods made with hydrogenated oils should be avoided because they contain high levels of trans fatty acids. The terms &quot;hydrogenated&quot; and &quot;saturated&quot; are related; an oil becomes saturated when hydrogen is added (i.e., becomes hydrogenated). </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="40">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PARTIALLY HYDROGENATED</text>

	<text>                   Refers to oils that have become partially hardened. Foods made with partially hydrogenated oils should also be avoided because they contain high levels of trans fatty acids.</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - FATS</text>

	<text>SATURATED FATS</text>

	<text>                   These are the biggest dietary cause of high LDL levels (&quot;bad cholesterol&quot;). Saturated fats are found in animal products such as butter, cheese, whole milk, ice cream, cream, and fatty meats. They are also found in some vegetable oils. These should also be avoided as much as possible. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="41">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>GOOD FATS</text>

	<text>                   The &quot;good&quot; fat – also known as Essential Fatty Acids (EFA’s).There are two families of EFA’s, Omega-3 (linolenic acid) and Omega-6 (linoleic acid).Omega-3 and Omega-6 EFA’s are the raw materials used to make all the special fats in the structure of your brain, eyes, ears, testes, ovaries, adrenals and the membranes that surround and protect every cell in your body. You must get EFA’s from your diet, because your body cannot make them.Omega-3 EFA’s are found in the body oils of cold-water ocean fish like cod, mackerel, tuna and also found in vegetable oils like Macadamia nut.The healing and preventive abilities of Omega-3 in fish oil have been documented in countless studies in the U.S. and Europe.</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - FATS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="42">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>GOOD FATS</text>

	<text>                   The most significant benefits of Omega-6 include ensuring fat regulation and energy distribution (which aids in weight-loss), and reducing the intensity of PMS symptoms. High concentrations of Omega-6 are found in safflower oil and Macadamia nut oil.In addition, Omega-6 assists Omega-3 in reducing all kinds of inflammation, lowering LDL cholesterol and promotes optimal immune function.</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - FATS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="43">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>GOOD FATS</text>

	<text>                   Burn fat: Helps the body eliminate excess fat.Prevent heart disease: Dramatically reduces the risk of heart disease by providing a slippery protective coat on the walls of the arteries, thus inhibiting plaque from sticking to arterial walls.Relieve Arthritis pain and inflammation: Extremely effective in relieving the symptoms of arthritic conditions by suppressing inflammation.Fight cancerous growths: Helps prevent cancer from growing by blocking cells that nourish the cancer.Reduce symptoms of PMS and Menopause: Help relieve the drying of vaginal and bladder tissues in menopausal women, which helps ward off urinary tract infections.</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - FATS</text>

	<text>                   The following are just some of the ways that the two families of EFA’s, Omega-3 and Omega-6 can benefit you:</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="44">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - FATS</text>

	<text>CHOOSING THE RIGHT OILS AND FATS</text>

	<text>SATURATED FATSAvoidButterCoconut OilPalm OilPalm Kernel OilAnimal FatCocoa ButterGheeMargerine</text>

	<text>POLYUNSATURATEDSome are goodFish Oils (good)Seasame Oils (good)Primrose Oils (good)Safflower OilCottonseed OilCorn OilPeanut OilSunflower Oil</text>

	<text>MONOUNSATURATEDAll goodMacadamia Nut OilOlive OilHigh-Oleic SunflowerHigh-Oleic SunflowerAvocado OilCanola Oil</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="45">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>GOOD FATS</text>

	<text>                   Although it is well documented that Omega 3 and Omega 6 are Essential Fatty acids, Omega 9 to a lesser degree is also considered important for Heart health and as such it is advisable to ensure you contain all these fats in your diet.Essential Fatty acids via supplementation if normal intake of fats is difficult</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - FATS</text>

	<text>                   Omega 3 – Fish OilsOmega 6 -  Evening Primrose oilOmega 9 – Macadamia nut oil</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="46">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>                   The word protein comes from the Greek word ‘proteios’ which means of great or primary importance.  Proteins are organic compounds made up of carbon, hydrogen, oxygen and nitrogen. It is the presence of the nitrogen which sets protein apart from other nutrients.Since we have no other source of nitrogen one of the most important roles of protein is to bring nitrogen into the body. Protein is thus broken down into amino acids within the body. </text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - PROTEIN</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="47">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ROLE OF PROTEIN</text>

	<text>                   Protein requirements of athletes are increased well above those of sedentary people,Due in part to changes in amino acid metabolism induced by intense </text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - PROTEIN</text>

	<text>ROLE OF PROTEIN / AMINO ACIDS ARE…</text>

	<text>                   Recovery, assisting immune suppressionBuild proteins of new tissueSupport new growth and maintenance of cells, and making of working parts of cellsFacilitate chemical reactions</text>

	<text>                   Provide energyGrowth &amp; maintenanceHormone productionTransportation i.e. HaemoglobinBlood clottingStructural components</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="48">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>RDA (RECOMMENDED DAILY ALLOWANCE)</text>

	<text>                   Contrary to what many dieticians believe, the RDA (Recommended daily allowance) was never meant to provide protein requirements for active individuals. Additionally, numerous studies have shown that exercise increases the need for protein (1,2).It’s important to understand that protein requirements most definitely increase in athletes. Data reviewed by Dr. Peter Lemon indicates that endurance athletes may need 1.2-1.4 g/kg of protein and strength athletes 1.6-1.8 g/kg to maintain a positive nitrogen balance (meaning that protein is being stored in the body) (3).</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - PROTEIN</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="49">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>RDA (RECOMMENDED DAILY ALLOWANCE)</text>

	<text>                   Dr. Peter Lemon also found that endurance athletes need 25-50 percentmore protein than the RDA, Dependent upon the intensity and duration of the activity.A study reported in The Physician and Sports Medicine showed that weight trainers (those who spend lots of time in the gym) need protein at a rate of 438 percent higher than the RDA. To keep them in a positive nitrogen balance, equating to about two to two and half grams per kilo of body weight.</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - PROTEIN</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="50">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PROTEIN INTAKE STUDIES</text>

	<text>                   A small study at the University of Illinois found that a protein-rich diet boosted the effects of exercise in women trying to lose weight,In the four-month study, a group that substituted high-quality proteins for foods high in carbohydrates lost more fat (including more abdominal fat) than a group that consumed the same number of calories but more carbohydrates,A &quot;high-exercise&quot; portion of that group lost even more weight, and almost 100 percent of it was fat. In the high-carbohydrate, high-exercise group, as much as 25 to 30 percent of weight lost was muscle.</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - PROTEIN</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="51">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PROTEIN INTAKE STUDIES</text>

	<text>                   Dr. Michael Colgan at The Colgan Institute in California created a guide for us to follow for protein ingestion.  It is based on activity levels and body weight, as shown in the table…Table taken from Optimum Sports Nutrition, pg. 151: Used by permission from Advanced Research Press and The Colgan Institute.</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - PROTEIN</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="52">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PROTEIN INTAKE STUDIES</text>

	<text>                   Dr. Colgan defines the different activity level classes as:</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - PROTEIN</text>

	<text>CLASS</text>

	<text>1 Strength2 Speed3 Endurance</text>

	<text>TRAINNING USED</text>

	<text>SPORT</text>

	<text>1 Speed2 Strength3 Endurance</text>

	<text>Endurancedominates</text>

	<text> Sprints, Jumping, Boxing, Wrestling, Karate, Judo, Women’s Gymnastics and most ball games.</text>

	<text>Middle and Long Distance Running, Triathlons, Cross-Country Skiing, Cycling, Racquetball, and Tennis.</text>

	<text>Weight training, Shot put, Javelin, Discus and Men’s Gymnastics.</text>

	<text>1</text>

	<text>2</text>

	<text>3</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="53">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PROTEIN FACTS</text>

	<text>                   Elite Australian male athletes are known to have a daily protein intake over 1.5g/kg (Burke et al. 1991)In healthy male athletes who consumed long term daily protein intake of up to 2.8 g protein/kg body weight, no negative effects on renal function were found (Poortmans &amp; Dellalieux 2000).There is no published evidence that a diet containing up to 2.8 g protein/kg/day produces adverse effects on kidney metabolism in athletes.In addition, no known association of protein intake with progressive renal insufficiency has been determined (Brandle et al. 1996).” (NH&amp;MRC 2005 p 259). </text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - PROTEIN</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="54">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>SHOULD I TAKE A PROTEIN?</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - PROTEIN</text>

	<text>                   Many health professionals imply that protein supplementation is unnecessary and that the recommended daily intake for protein is easily achieved via normal dietary intake. However, this argument is based on the assumption that everyone consumes a well balanced diet containing a range of high quality protein sources. In today&apos;s hectic world how many people actually achieve this? If you don&apos;t achieve your recommended daily intake of protein each and every day a protein supplement MAY definitely be of benefit. A good guideline to follow in terms of nutrients on a plate is this formula: 1/3 Protein to 2/3’s good nutrient rich complex/fibrous carbohydrates.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="55">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>REFERENCES</text>

	<text>MACRO NUTRIENTS - PROTEIN</text>

	<text>                   Lemon, PWR et. al. &quot;Protein requirements and muscle mass/strength changes during intensive training in novice bodybuilders&quot; J App Phys (1992) 73: 767-775.Tarnopolsky, MA et. al. &quot;Evaluation of protein requirements for trained strength athletes&quot; J Appl Physiol (1992) 73: 1986-1995.Peter Lemon &quot;Is increased dietary protein necessary or beneficial for individuals with a physically active lifestyle&quot; Nutr Rev (1996) 54: S169-S175.J.P. Mullin and Lemon, P.R. &quot;Effect of initial muscle glycogen level on protein catabolism during exercise&quot; J Appl Physiol (1980) 48: 624-629.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="56">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PRE AND POST WORKOUT MEALS</text>

	<text>                   The chosen athletic endeavourer, i.e. a distance runner’s pre-event meal would be more unique compared to a, weight resistance workout meal. Duration of workout or competition, Bodyweight and environmental conditions,Timings of meal ingestion. i.e. a meal consumed 20 minutes pre- event would be somewhat different that a meal consumed three hours prior. Length of workout / competition. i.e. energy expenditure would be higher for a 90 minute session compared to a 30 minute session; hence meal size and macro nutrient ratios would alter accordingly, andTimings of workouts. i.e. training first thing in the morning compared to later in the day. </text>

	<text>                   To determine an appropriate meal selection in particular the pre-event / workout meals, there are many factors that should be taken into consideration such as…</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="57">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PRE AND POST WORKOUT MEALS</text>

	<text>PRE-EVENT MEALS</text>

	<text>                   It is generally accepted and often recommended that the pre-event meal predominately contains a suitable source of carbohydrates whilst maintaining a low fat content. However remembering this is coherent on the previously mentioned considerations. The pre-event meal has different goals than the post workout meal, The goal of the pre-event meal is to provide all the necessary specific nutrients for energy production to allow the athlete to perform effectively,It has now being scientifically verified that consuming a portion of protein combined with a carbohydrate source preferably in liquid form for digestibility issues before a workout reduces the possibility of muscle wastage. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="58">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PRE AND POST WORKOUT MEALS</text>

	<text>PRE-EVENT MEALS</text>

	<text>                   The idealistic timing for this method  would be for example a weight training session being performed first thing in the morning were the trainee would consume a small portion of protein and carbohydrates approximately 20 - 40 minutes prior to commencement. Without adequate supplies of the necessary nutrients the body can and will use other substrates for energy production (muscle loss). This obviously will in turn affect performance outcomes. This is not suited to every athletic endeavour as the specifity principle must apply however it pertains to the vast majority.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="59">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PRE AND POST WORKOUT MEALS</text>

	<text>POST WORKOUT MEALS</text>

	<text>                   The goal of this meal is to effectuate efficient recovery from training or competition. The timings of this meal are of paramount importance as delayed ingestion of nutrients causes a chain of negative effects within the body which hampers recovery substantially. The body has, which is often referred to as, a window of opportunity post training which allows a higher uptake of nutrients to assist in things such as glycogen/ATP replaced thus maximising recovery. This window in relation to time is generally accepted to be approximately three hours however this is dependant on the timing of the first meal post workout. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="60">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PRE AND POST WORKOUT MEALS</text>

	<text>POST WORKOUT MEALS</text>

	<text>                   The main opportunity window appears to be in the first 45 minutes of completing the workout.  If a meal is ingested within this time frame then the window will stay open but decrease as time passes. If a meal is not consumed within this time frame then the window of opportunity diminishes quickly and sets of a negative chain of events. Through the process of training intensely the body is able to digest a larger amount of nutrients post workout than any other time. In light of this finding it is recommended that your largest meal should be post workout consisting of a quality carbohydrate and protein source.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="61">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PRE AND POST WORKOUT MEALS</text>

	<text>POST WORKOUT MEALS</text>

	<text>                   However the problem lies within the fact that after training most people have difficulty in eating let alone consuming a large solid meal. The answer therefore often is consuming a liquid source of nutrients immediately finishing training and consuming a solid meal within 90 minutes of completing workout/event. Liquid sources allows quick effective nutrient uptake which is ideal for post workout/event requirements. The post workout meal should consist of a quality carbohydrate and protein source. This may be as suggested in liquid form. Preference is always given to solid meals however post workout is differently an exception.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="62">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>PRE AND POST WORKOUT MEALS</text>

	<text>POST WORKOUT MEALS</text>

	<text>                   A fast absorbing protein such as Whey protein isolate and a high glycemic carbohydrate source such as dextrose is an ideal combination. It is scientifically accepted that fast nutrient uptake post workout is important to maximise recovery. Potential supplementation that can be utilised to assist recovery and is commonly found amongst educated elite athletes is:</text>

	<text>                   Glutamine,Branch chain amino acids,Protein powder such as, Whey Protein Isolate (WPI), andCarbohydrate source such as dextrose or maltodextrin</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="63">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>FOOD LABELING</text>

	<text>WHY DO WE NEED TO HAVE FOOD LABELS?</text>

	<text>                   Tell us which nutrients, in what amounts, are in a product Warn us if a food contains food allergens Inform us if the food is fresh or out of date Explain how to store, prepare or cook the food we buy List product ingredientsGive us information  on where the food was produced and by which company</text>

	<text>Food labels provide information to help us make healthier and safer food choices. They                  </text>

	<text>Essentially, food labels are there to provide us with basic information about what is in the food we eat and how nest to handle it.                  </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="64">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>

	<text>WHAT LABELLING TRICKS YOU?</text>

	<text>                   Food labels tell us exactly what we are paying for, so it really does pay to take the time to read them In Australia all packaged and manufactured foods must have a food label and nutrition information panel. By law, they must be accurate and not contain misleading informationNutrition information is available on every food label. It can help us to make healthier and informed food choices, resulting in better health. Understanding how to read a label will help you make sure you are making the best choices for you and your client.Food manufacturers commonly use words, statements or symbols on food packets that can often be confusing and misleading causing consumers to think that a particular product is a healthier choice. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="65">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>

	<text>FOOD LABELS MUST PROVIDE</text>

	<text>                   Name of the foodBest before or Use by dateIngredients list - listed from greatest to smallest weightDeclaration of potential allergens - such as nuts, seafood, milk, eggs and glutenList of food additives - found in the ingredients listDeclaration of genetically modified ingredientsStorage informationManufacturers name and addressCountry of origin</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="66">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>

	<text>WHAT LABELLING TRICKS YOU?</text>

	<text>                   Light or Lite: Doesn’t always mean lower in fat or kilojoules. It may mean less salt or even just a “light” texture or tasteNo cholesterol: This doesn’t necessarily mean low fat. Vegetable foods do not contain cholesterol (only animal foods have cholesterol) but vegetable oils may be high in total and saturated fat. Saturated fat can raise your blood cholesterol levels97% fat free: The food contains no more than 3% fat or 3g of fat per 100g. These foods are low in fat. However, they may still be high in sugar and kilojoulesReduced fat: This means the food has less fat than the standard product. However these foods are usually NOT low in fat</text>

	<text>                   Here are some examples:</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="67">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>

	<text>WHAT LABELLING TRICKS YOU?</text>

	<text>Here are some examples:</text>

	<text>                   No added sugars: Sugar is not added to the food, but the food may be naturally high in sugars, which may also make it high in kilojoulesDiet or low-joule: These foods usually have artificial sweetenersNo added salt or reduced salt: Salt has not been added or the normal quantity has been reduced. Reduced salt foods are not necessarily low salt foodsHigh fibre: The food</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="68">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>

	<text>WHAT ARE THE COMMON NAMES ON LABELS?</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="69">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>

	<text>GETTING THE MOST FROM NUTRITION INFORMATION PANELS</text>

	<text>                   Per 100g: Useful standard to compare one brand against anotherEnergy / Kilojoules: The energy value is the total amount of kilojoules from protein, fat, carbohydrate, dietary fibre and alcohol that is released when food is used by the body.Protein:  It includes both animal sources such as meat, poultry, fish, eggs, milk and cheese AND plant sources such as lentils, dried peas and beans, nuts and cereals.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="70">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>

	<text>GETTING THE MOST FROM NUTRITION INFORMATION PANELS</text>

	<text>                   Fat: Low fat foods have no more than 3 grams of fat per 100g. Foods with higher fat contents can be healthy choices if the saturated fat content is low. Children (especially those under 2 years of age) need some higher fat foodsSaturated fats: Look for less than 3g per 100gCarbohydrate:  Found in bread, cereals, rice, pasta, milk, vegetables and fruit. It includes both starches and sugars. Starches are found in high amounts in foods such as white, wholemeal and wholegrain varieties of cereal, breads, rice and pasta, together with root vegetables and legumes.Sugars: Most natural, unprocessed foods have sugar contents less than 15 grams per 100g. Naturally occurring sugars e.g.. Those in dairy and fruit are better choices than added sugars</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="71">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>

	<text>GETTING THE MOST FROM NUTRITION INFORMATION PANELS</text>

	<text>                   Dietary fibre: Pick a product that is higher in fibre (per 100g), especially when comparing cereals, bread, biscuitsSodium: Where possible, choose products with reduced or no added salt. Low salt products have less than 120mg per 100g. Try to always choose products with less than 400mg salt per 100g.Ingredients: Manufacturers must list ingredients in terms of quantity. Thus ingredients listed first will be found in the largest amounts in that food.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="72">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>

	<text>FOOD LABELS MUST PROVIDE</text>

	<text>                   Name of the foodBest before or Use by dateIngredients list - listed from greatest to smallest weightDeclaration of potential allergens - such as nuts, seafood, milk, eggs and glutenList of food additives - found in the ingredients listDeclaration of genetically modified ingredientsStorage informationManufacturers name and addressCountry of origin</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="73">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="74">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="75">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="76">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="77">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="78">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="79">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>WHAT LABELLING TRICKS YOU?</text>

	<text>                   It is important to remember, when suggesting food choices for your clients, that you are aware of food labelling methods. Many of these methods are employed by the manufacturer to entice the consumer to buy their specific products.Remember the three steps to selling This generally starts approximately 3 steps away from the product shelfLabels deliberately market (highlight) key points that influence your purchase choiceMany manufacturers display “trigger” words that are associated with good health and diet Low GI - 99% Fat free – No added sugar etc.</text>

	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="80">
	<title></title>

	<content></content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="81">
	<title></title>

	<content></content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="82">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="83">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>READING FOOD LABELS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="84">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>10 MOST POPULAR DIETS:</text>

	<text>                   Atkins Diet,Detox Diets,Jenny Craig Diet,Lite n’ Easy,Mediterranean Diet,Tony Ferguson Diet,Vegetarian Diet,Weight Watcher’s,CSIRO - Total Wellbeing Diet,Blood Type Diets</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="85">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>ATKINS DIET</text>

	<text>                   Principally low carbohydrates, moderate protein, low fat but does recommend EFA’s however there is some saturated fat included in various recipes. </text>

	<text>                   Phase 1 – Introduction - Days 1-14, 20 grams of carbohydrates only and an increase in activity levelsPhase 2 – Ongoing weigh loss (OWL) - Introduction of carbohydrates back into the diet. Determines personal threshold level of carbohydrate consumption – Called  CCL - Critical Carbohydrate Level for Losing. You&apos;ll stay on OWL until you are within approximately 5kgs of your goal then you move onto Pre-Maintenance Phase.</text>

	<text>                   Four Phases: </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="86">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>                   Phase 3 – Pre-maintenance - During Pre-Maintenance, you&apos;ll keep adding good carbs to your diet each week and continue to lose until you reach your point of equilibrium - the point where you don&apos;t lose, or gain any more weight.Atkins advocates call this magic number your Atkins Carbohydrate Equilibrium, or ACE, You should of Achieved your goal weightPhase 4 – Lifetime maintenance - Person maintains eating habits and increasing activity levels to achieve a healthy lifestyle and bodyweight. There is also on going support to maintain lifestyle thus healthy weight.</text>

	<text>ATKINS DIET</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="87">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>DETOX DIETS</text>

	<text>                   Detox advocates believe that certain foods are toxic to the body, particularly refined and acid-forming foods. When our bodies break down these refined sugars, they produce a by-product of acidic deposits (toxins) that accumulate to cause a sluggish digestive system. By ‘detoxing’ it is believed, you eliminate these toxins from your diet, giving the digestive system the chance to function more efficiently, helping you to burn off more calories.</text>

	<text>Detox programs health claims of improving:</text>

	<text>                   Bowel health, Revitalizing the skin and liver, Increasing energy levels, and Aiding in weight loss</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="88">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>                   A standard detox will involve a clean-up of your diet.  The revised diet is then based on fruit, vegetables and water, while cutting out meat (optional), alcohol, caffeine and processed foods.On a detox, you should try to eat as much organic and raw food as possible.  You are also encouraged to eat plenty of dark green leafy vegetables, brown rice, soups and vegetable juice.  Water also plays a prominent role.</text>

	<text>DETOX DIETS</text>

	<text>Methods</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="89">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>                   As detox programs have not yet been clearly defined, it is impossible to judge whether or not they work. Advocates assert that detox programs encourage healthy eating patterns however critics argue that there is no evidence to support the belief that such detox regimes help remove toxins from the body. They claim that the lungs, kidneys, liver, gastrointestinal tract and immune systems already remove or neutralize toxic substances.</text>

	<text>DETOX DIETS</text>

	<text>Science?</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="90">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>JENNY CRAIG DIET</text>

	<text>                   Calorie controlled meals delivered to your door with ongoing phone and consultancy support. </text>

	<text>                   With Jenny Craig, you will get…</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="91">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>JENNY CRAIG DIET</text>

	<text>ONE-ON-ONE WEEKLY PHONE SUPPORT</text>

	<text>                   Each week, you&apos;ll speak privately with your skilled Consultant via phone to plan your weekly menu and activities, discuss strategies to overcome challenges along the way, and celebrate your successes. An integral part of the Jenny Craig Program, these weekly consultations play a major role in the clients&apos; successes.</text>

	<text>CONVENIENT FOOD DELIVERY STRAIGHT TO YOUR HOME OR OFFICE</text>

	<text>                   You&apos;ll order your Jenny Craig Cuisine from your Consultant which will be delivered to your home or office within 48 hours in two or four-week</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="92">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>JENNY CRAIG DIET</text>

	<text>THREE TYPES OF ACTIVITIES</text>

	<text>Activity levels are encourage to be increased and are suggested in the following manner:</text>

	<text>NaturalMake the most of everyday activities such as washing dishes or light cleaning - even shopping!</text>

	<text>PlannedA well-rounded fitness plan includes:cardio, resistance, &amp; stretching activities - try walking, pilates or yoga</text>

	<text>PlayfulBe active and have fun with family and friends - try dancing, cycling, or playing with your kids!</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="93">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>LITE n’ EASY</text>

	<text>                   Calorie controlled meals delivered to the person’s home providing a weekly meal selection. Ranges from 1200 cal to 1800calRecommendations on their web site to be involved in exercise and suggested 30mins a day as a starting point.Utilizes BMI as a method to assess body composition Level of Perceived Exertion used as a means of assessing exercise levels and suggestions on most appropriate exercise choices for fat loss </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="94">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>MEDITERRANEAN DIET</text>

	<text>                   Based on &quot;food patterns typical of Crete, much of the rest of Greece, and southern Italy in the early 1960s“……this diet, in addition to &quot;regular physical activity “…</text>

	<text>Emphasizes</text>

	<text>                   Abundant plant foods,Fresh fruit as the typical daily dessert, Olive oil as the principal source of fat, Dairy products (principally cheese and yogurt), Fish and poultry consumed in low to moderate amounts, Zero to four eggs consumed weekly, Red meat consumed in low amounts, andWine consumed in low to moderate amounts“.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="95">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>Total fat in this diet is 25% to 35% of calories, with saturated fat at 8% or less of calories. The diet is often cited as beneficial for being low in saturated fat and high in monounsaturated fat  and dietary fibre… One of the main explanations is thought to be the large amount of olive oil  used in the Mediterranean diet. Unlike the high amount of animal fats  typical to the American diet, olive oil lowers cholesterol levels in the blood. It is also known to lower blood sugar  levels and blood pressure.</text>

	<text>MEDITERRANEAN DIET</text>

	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="96">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>MEDITERRANEAN DIET</text>

	<text>Research indicates olive oil is heart healthy and may be a factor in preventing cancer. </text>

	<text>In addition, the consumption of red wine is considered a possible factor, as it contains resveratrol – a powerful antioxidant. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="97">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>The Seven Countries Study found that Cretan men had exceptionally low death rates from heart disease, despite moderate to high intake of fat. The Cretan diet is similar to other traditional Mediterranean diets: consisting mostly of olive oil, bread, abundant fruit and vegetables, fish, and a moderate amount of dairy foods and wine.</text>

	<text>TONY FERGUSON DIET</text>

	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="98">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>On the Program, you&apos;ll replace two meals a day, such as breakfast and lunch, with one of their shakes or soups, with supplements in the morning. For dinner it is suggested to consume a lean steak, chicken breast or a meal from the Tony Ferguson cookbook.On going support as stated by his web site,Regular progress weigh-ins,  Support and friendly guidance if you feel   things aren&apos;t going as they should, Advice on food and nutrition in conjunction with the Program, Professional assistance with any weight loss related medical concerns, and More supplies of the soups and shakes, essential Program supplements, Simply Diet Jelly and other snacks</text>

	<text>TONY FERGUSON DIET</text>

	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="99">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>1 x Tony Ferguson meal replacement shake1 x Simply Balanced multivitamin tablet1 x Simply Chromium dietary supplement capsule</text>

	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>TONY FERGUSON DIET</text>

	<text>DIETARY RECOMMENDATIONS</text>

	<text>Breakfast</text>

	<text>1 x Serve of fresh fruit* </text>

	<text>Mid-morning </text>

	<text>1 x Tony Ferguson meal replacement shake or soup with two teaspoons of Tony Ferguson Simply Fibre added1 x Fresh, home-made salad* </text>

	<text>Lunch</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="100">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>1 x Serve of fresh fruit*</text>

	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>TONY FERGUSON DIET</text>

	<text>DIETARY RECOMMENDATIONS</text>

	<text>Mid-afternoon </text>

	<text>1 x Palm-sized piece of protein* A minimum of three cups of fresh vegetables* </text>

	<text>Dinner</text>

	<text>Unlimited Simply Diet Jelly or a 100 calorie snack** For maximum weight loss benefits, all fruit, vegetables, protein and 100 calorie snacks should be selected from our allowed food lists. It is suggested you refer to the  Tony Ferguson Weight Management Book for details.</text>

	<text>After Dinner</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="101">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>Some people follow a &quot;vegetarian&quot; diet, but there&apos;s no single vegetarian eating pattern.The vegan or total vegetarian diet includes only foods from plants: fruits, vegetables, legumes (dried beans and peas), grains, seeds and nuts.</text>

	<text>VEGETARIAN DIET</text>

	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="102">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>The Lacto-vegetarian diet includes plant foods plus cheese and other dairy products.The Ovo-lacto-vegetarian  diet also includes eggs. Semi-vegetarians don&apos;t eat red meat but include chicken and fish with plant foods, dairy products and eggs</text>

	<text>VEGETARIAN DIET</text>

	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="103">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>How the POINTS system worksEvery food has a POINTS value, which is calculated based on a food’s kilojoules and saturated fat. POINTS values help you keep track of what you eat, so that you stay within a daily POINTS Target that’s personalised for you, based on your height, weight and other factors, such as gender. Along with your daily POINTS Target, you also get a “Weekly Allowance” to use for a special occasion like a night on the town, so you can still indulge sometimes, without going off track.</text>

	<text>WEIGHT WATCHERS</text>

	<text>POINTS FOR FOOD CONSUMPTION</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="104">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>The “Four Pillars” of the Weight Watchers approach promote healthy habits, a supportive environment, and exercise, in addition to making smarter food choices..</text>

	<text>WEIGHT WATCHERS</text>

	<text>FOUR PILLAR SYSTEM FOR SUPPORT</text>

	<text>Meetings provide a motivating and informative environment led by a Leader who has lost weight with Weight Watchers and kept it off. Each weigh-in is confidential. Plus, you can subscribe to e-Tools, the Internet companion for Meetings..</text>

	<text>REGULAR MEETINGS WITH WEIGH-INS WORKING ON BMI STANDARDS</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="105">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>CSIRO – TOTAL WELLBEING DIET</text>

	<text>The diet is based on a study published in the American Journal of Clinical Nutrition which compared the weight loss between two groups…...both receiving the same amount of daily calorie intake, but one on a high carbohydrate diet and the other on a high protein diet.The study showed that both groups lost weight, but those on the high protein diet lost more and felt better.This group lost more weight on the high protein diet, but most importantly, they lost twice the amount of body fat, and markers indicating risk of heart disease and diabetes improved significantly.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="106">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>CSIRO – TOTAL WELLBEING DIET</text>

	<text>A long term study done after a year on the high protein diet showed that dieters had managed to maintain weight loss, and on average were 3 kilograms lighter than their counterparts on the high carbohydrate diet.CSIRO has spent the past few years exploring the healthiest and most successful ways to lose weight. In recent studies they demonstrated the benefits of an eating plan that provides more protein and less refined carbohydrates. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="107">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>CSIRO – TOTAL WELLBEING DIET</text>

	<text>CSIRO has ALSO conducted several of the largest studies showing that higher protein dietary patterns for weight management have metabolic advantages over high carbohydrate patterns in overweight people.The results clearly showed health benefits and significant weight loss from a diet higher in proteins and low in fats and the Total Wellbeing Diet was born. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="108">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>BLOOD TYPE DIETS</text>

	<text>Although blood type diets have gained popularity of late, there is little, if any, publicized research on their affects. It is commonly accepted that certain foods will have an allergenic response to certain people, and as such, should be avoided.There are blood tests available that will test your allergenic response to foods. These are more accurate in determining suitable food types specific to the individual needs, as apposed to a generalized classification as seen in blood typing.According to Dr. Peter DÁdamo, author of Eat Right For Your Type, a chemical reaction occurs between your blood and the foods you eat.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="109">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>CSIRO – TOTAL WELLBEING DIET</text>

	<text>This reaction is part of your genetic inheritance. His theory is based on the idea that each blood group has its own unique antigen marker (a substance that the body recognises as being alien) and this marker reacts badly with certain foods, leading to all sorts of potential health problems</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="110">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>BLOOD TYPE DIETS</text>

	<text>This is the most common blood group found. Dr D’Adamo says that our digestive tract retains the memory of ancient times, and so type Os need to eat a typical hunter-gatherer type diet. In other words, type Os should follow a high-protein, low-carb diet with lots of meat and fish but no dairy products, wheat or grains.</text>

	<text>BLOOD GROUP O</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="111">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>This is the second most common blood type found.  Again according to Dr D&apos;Adamo, digestive system is apparently very good at remembering that our ancestors had settled, farming lifestyles, which included eating lots of grains and vegetables but little meat.</text>

	<text>BLOOD TYPE DIETS</text>

	<text>BLOOD GROUP O</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="112">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>BLOOD TYPE DIETS</text>

	<text>Diet Profile</text>

	<text>Allowed</text>

	<text>Limited</text>

	<text>Food to avoid for Weight Loss purpose</text>

	<text>Food that help with Weight Loss </text>

	<text>Type O</text>

	<text>Type A</text>

	<text>High Protein:Meat eaters</text>

	<text>Vegetarian</text>

	<text>Meatfishvegetablesfruit</text>

	<text>vegetablestofuseafoodgrainsbeanslegumesfruit</text>

	<text>meatdairykidney beanslima beanswheat</text>

	<text>wheatcornkidney beansnavy beanslentilscabbageBrussels sproutscauliflowermustard greens</text>

	<text>kelpseafoodsaltliverred meatkalespinachbroccoli</text>

	<text>vegetable oil soy foodsvegetablespineapple</text>

	<text>grainsbeanslegumes </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="113">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>POPULAR DIETS</text>

	<text>BLOOD TYPE DIETS</text>

	<text>Diet Profile</text>

	<text>Allowed</text>

	<text>Limited</text>

	<text>Food to avoid for Weight Loss purpose</text>

	<text>Food that help with Weight Loss </text>

	<text>Type B</text>

	<text>Type AB</text>

	<text>Balanced omnivore</text>

	<text>Mixed diet in moderation</text>

	<text>meat (no chicken)dairygrainsbeanslegumesvegetables fruit</text>

	<text>meatseafooddairytofubeanslegumesgrainsvegetablesfruits</text>

	<text>red meatkidney beanslima beansseedscornbuckwheat</text>

	<text>cornlentilpeanutssesameseedsbuckwheatwheat</text>

	<text>greenseggsvenisonliverlicoricetea</text>

	<text>tofuseafooddairygreenskelppineapple</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="114">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ARTIFICIAL SWEETNERS</text>

	<text>ASPARTAME OVERVIEW</text>

	<text>Discovered in 1965, aspartame is a low-calorie sweetener with a sugar-like taste but is approximately 200 times sweeter than sucrose,Aspartame is unique among low-calorie sweeteners in that it is completely broken down by the body to its components – the amino acids, aspartic acid and phenylalanine, and a small amount of methanol (Methyl ester), andCurrently, aspartame is found in more than 6,000 products and is consumed by over 200 million people around the world.</text>

	<text>PROPOSED BENEFITS</text>

	<text>Tastes Sweet and Clean - Studies conducted show that aspartame&apos;s taste is very similar to the taste of sugar,Enhances and Extends Flavors - Aspartame has the ability to intensify and extend fruit flavors,Does Not Promote Tooth DecayIs Helpful for Individuals with Diabetes - allows them to satisfy their taste for sweets without affecting blood sugar. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="115">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ARTIFICIAL SWEETNERS</text>

	<text>ACESULFAME POTASSIUM</text>

	<text>…is a non-caloric sweetener, discovered in 1967, acesulfame potassium (also known as acesulfame K) is approximately 200 times sweeter than sucrose. It has a clean, sweet taste that does not linger or leave an aftertaste. It is not metabolized by the body and is excreted unchanged.</text>

	<text>PROPOSED BENEFITS</text>

	<text>Helps Reduce Calories— Since acesulfame K is not metabolized, it contributes no calories,Remains Stable Under High Temperatures— The sweet taste of acesulfame K remains unchanged during baking,Tastes Sweet and Clean— Acesulfame K generally does not exhibit any off-taste in foods and soft drinks,Does Not Promote Tooth Decay, and Useful in Diabetic Diets— Studies have shown that acesulfame K has no effect on serum glucose, cholesterol, or triglycerides. </text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="116">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ARTIFICIAL SWEETNERS</text>

	<text>SUCRALOSE</text>

	<text>Discovered in 1976, Sucralose is the only non-caloric sweetener made from sugar through a multi-step patented manufacturing process, This change produces a sweetener that has no calories, yet is 600 times sweeter than sucrose. It tastes like sugar and does not leave an unpleasant aftertaste,  Sucralose is not utilized for energy in the body because it is not broken down like sucrose,It passes rapidly through the body virtually unchanged</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="117">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ARTIFICIAL SWEETNERS</text>

	<text>CYCLAMATE</text>

	<text>Cyclamate is a non-caloric sweetener discovered in 1937. It has been used widely in low-calorie foods and beverages. Most people do not metabolise cyclamate. </text>

	<text>SACCHARIN</text>

	<text>Saccharin is 300 times sweeter than sugar, which means only a little is needed for sweetening. However, like most artificial sweeteners, it has an unpleasant, bitter aftertaste. It is stable when heated. It also passes through the body without having any impact on the blood sugar levels.</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="118">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>ARTIFICIAL SWEETNERS</text>

	<text>SUGAR ALCOHOLS OR POLYOLS</text>

	<text>Sugar alcohols are sugar-free sweeteners, Sugar alcohols are carbohydrates but they are not sugars,These are often not listed as the total carbohydrate of the product, and Sugar Alcohols are (Hydrogenated starch):</text>

	<text>hydrolysates - 3.0 cal / gSorbitol - 2.6 cal / gXylitol - 2.4 cal / gMaltitol - 2.1 cal / g</text>

	<text>Isomalt - 2.0 cal / gLactitol - 2.0 cal / gMannitol - 1.6 cal / gErythritol - 0.2 cal / g</text>
</content>
</section>
<section type="slide" position="119">
	<title></title>

	<content>
	<text>Assessment / conclusion page</text>
</content>
</section>
</document-metadata>
